Good afternoon,
everyone. My name
is Dr. Mervat
Mourad. Today, we're
going to continue
the discussion about
acute coronary
syndromes and MI.
This is part two of
the lecture. Part
one was discussed by
our academic medicine
scholar, Stratos,
who did a great work
in explaining ischemic
heart disease,
stable angina, and
vasospastic angina.
special thanks to
our previous academic
medicine scholar
who collaborated
in this work over years
and we continue to
do so this year
so we updated our
presentation we made it
relevant we trimmed the
unnecessary things to
try to be more focused
so I hope you enjoy
the presentation.
Here are the session
objectives. By the
end of this session,
I expect you to be
able to relay the
pertinent clinical features
of acute MI during
a focused cardiac
exam. You will be able
to classify acute MI
based on the clinical
findings, ECG
findings, and laboratory
findings. You will
be able to explain
the role of risk
stratification in the
prediction of risk when
managing patients with
acute ischemic events.
You will be able
to demonstrate the
awareness of the
complication of acute MI.
And here is a
session outline.
Basically, it's
a roadmap that
highlights what we're
going to discuss.
We'll start with introduction
to acute coronary
syndrome. Acute
coronary syndrome is an
umbrella term used
to describe range of
clinical condition associated
with a sudden severe
decrease in the blood
flow to the heart
causing symptoms such
as chest pain shortness
of breath etc and it
includes three things
unstable angina non
-stemi and stemi and here
there is a schematic
for the pathogenesis
of acute coronary
syndrome we put it for you
to um you can watch it
on your leisure time
basically um you know
it's a refresher for
what you uh studied
in pathology or you
learned in pathology so
i'm not gonna consume
the time going over
that i'm gonna switch
to our patient now who
is 47 year old black
male that present to
the ED complaining
of chest pain states
the pain is constant and
it reduced to the
left shoulder describe
the pain as a squeezing
sensation in the
middle of the chest
began approximately 30
minutes ago and 10
out of 10 on the *****
scale he was given
sublingual nitroglycerin
in the ambulance on the
way to the ED without
relief has risk
factors of hypertension
and hyperlipidemia,
and his medication
include amlidipine 10 mg
daily and rosovastatin
20 mg daily, which
are antihypertensive
and antihypercholesterolemic,
respectively.
On physical exam,
patient is tachycardiac,
diaphoretic, and clenching
his fists over his
sternum. What is the
suspected diagnosis?
And this basically,
you know, the term
acute coronary
syndrome is applied
to patient in whom
there is a suspicion
or a confirmation
of acute myocardial
ischemia or
infarction. And as we
said before, it includes
three things or
three conditions,
unstable angina, non
-STEMI, and STEMI.
And as we mentioned,
the diagnosis based
on history and
the physical or
clinical presentation,
serial ECGs, and the
cardiac biomarkers.
And let's learn
more about unstable
angina. Unstable
angina is characterized
by partial or
subtotal occlusion,
about 90% of the
coronary artery,
leading to
subendocardial ischemia.
Subendocardial
ischemia. So in
unstable angina,
there is something
called subendocardial
ischemia.
characterized by acute
severe sub-sternal
chest pain with
increasing frequency or
intensity or duration
occurs at rest and not
relieved by sublingual
nitroglycerin and lasts
more than 10 minutes
when it comes to the
ecg finding there may
be present or absent
um you know In terms
of, you may find ST
depression and or T
wave inversion, or you
may not, which are
indicative of ischemia.
Usually, troponins
and CKMB are normal
because there is no
cardiac myonecrosis
when it comes to
unstable angina.
When it comes to
non-STEMI, there is
also partial or
subtotal occlusion
of about 90% of the
coronary artery,
leading to
subendocardial ischemia.
It's characterized
by acute severe
sub-external chest
pain with increasing
frequency or
intensity or duration.
There's some associated
symptoms like
radiation to the
left shoulder or jaw,
diaphoresis, tachycardia
usually occurs
at rest and not
relieve the sublingual
nitroglycerin
and last more
than 10 minutes.
When it comes to
the ECG features,
you may find
ST depression
and or T wave inversion,
which is indicative
of ischemia, or you
may not. So the ECG
finding is variable.
When it comes to
the troponin and the
CKMP, there is positive
cardiac biomarkers
or elevated cardiac
biomarkers since there
is myocardial necrosis.
So in non-STEMI,
there is myocardial
necrosis occlusion,
was, you know,
significant, and was
able to produce
myocardial muscle death.
And that's why we see
elevated troponins.
when it comes to STEMI
which is ST elevation
in my eye there is
total occlusion 100
% occlusion of the
coronary artery which
leads to something
called the transmural
ischemia so the ischemia
in STEMI is transmural
across the myocardial
muscle across the
whole width of the
myocardial muscle so
characterized by acute
severe sub sternal
chest pain with
increasing frequency or
intensity or duration
usually associated with
radiation to the left
shoulder or the jaw,
diaphoresis, tachycardia,
and sometimes
hypotension, and
eventually shock
if the blood
pressure is
critically low.
Usually occurs at
rest and not relieved
with sublingual
nitroglycerin, and
the pain lasts more
than 10 minutes.
The ECG is
characteristic for ST
elevation and or it
may show something
called the new lift
bundle branch block.
If you see new lift
bundle branch block on
someone that's equal to
ST elevation MI because
that means there is
acute ischemia of the
conduction system which
leads to a picture
similar to a left
bundle branch
block so you
treat new left
bundle branch
block as mi exactly
or ischemia the
cardiac biomarkers
are elevated
because there
is transmural
ischemia which has
led to myocardial
necrosis and this slide
lay out the differences
between both basically
it's a summary slide
to what we said so when
it comes to the pain
presentation exactly
pretty much similar
among the three when it
comes to myocardial
necrosis in unstable
angina there is no
myocardial necrosis because
likely still it's
like anginal like pain
but it's more severe
more prolonged and and
and you know occlusion
is more significant but
maybe there are some
reversible moment so
it's the subendocardial
ischemia is not enough
to or not sustained
to cause myocardial
necrosis in contrast
to non-STEMI and STEMI
where there is
myocardial necrosis.
And that will
correlate to the
myocardial or
cardiac biomarkers.
So no biomarkers are
detected in
unstable angina.
The troponin and the
CKMP are elevated
in non-STEMI
because there is
myonecrosis and
the STEMI as well.
Okay? The occlusion,
the percentage of
the occlusion in
unstable angina,
about 90%, non-STEMI
about 90% occlusion,
and inSTEMI is 100
% total occlusion.
And when it comes
to the ECG features,
they are non-specific.
You can see some
signs indicative like
ST depression, ST,
T wave inversion,
suggestive of iskemia.
You may not. The
same thing applies
to non-STEMI, but
in STEMI, you will
see ST elevation
or new left bundle
branch block. So
keep that in mind.
back to our patient
about what's us what
is a suspected diagnosis
and here are the
salient features of
the presentation chest
pain constant radiates
to the left shoulder
approximately 30 minutes
10 out of 10 so severe
sublinked while
nitroglycerin didn't
give him any relief
has some risk
factors, hypertension,
hyperlipidemia and
he was also noted
to be tachycardiac,
diaphoretic and
the clenching his
physis over the sternum
on physical exam
and here are the
options GERD,
costochondritis,
stable angina panic
disorder, acute
coronary syndrome.
GERD, our patient
doesn't have a history
of GERD and also
there is no heartburn
or anything suggestive
of GERD. Second,
GERD pain is not
the chest pain
that is produced
by GERD is not
very severe as in
our patient here
in this case.
Costochondritis,
usually patient has
reproducible pain, and
usually when you press
the costochondral
junction, it reproduce
the pain, so it's not.
Stable angina, usually
exertional, relieved
by rest or sublingual
nitroglycerin,
usually lasts less
than 10 minutes so it's
not um the case in
our patient panic
disorder patient
doesn't have any history
suggestive of panic
disorder um patient also
doesn't have history
of anxiety and there
is no mention of sense
of impending doom
or anything like that
so it's not really
panic disorder and
And usually panic
disorder is a diagnosis
of exclusion for
somebody with chest
pain. We have to be sure
all other causes of
chest pain are negative
to label somebody
with panic disorder.
Acute coronary syndrome
sound reasonable.
Suspected diagnosis.
So the correct
answer is E.
Okay. Back to our
patient. Now we are
suspicious about acute
coronary syndrome.
What would be the
most appropriate
next step in management
of this patient?
okay send for emergency
cardiac catheterization
electrocardiogram
and the cardiac
biomarkers cardiology
consultation chest x-ray
troponin levels so
we have to establish
diagnosis first before
of STEMI or non-STEMI
before we send him to the
cardiac catheterization
um so electrocardiogram
and the cardiac
biomarkers along
with history seems a
reasonable option and
that's the way it goes
um cardiology consultation
we need to um see
what's going on with
him first and establish
a diagnosis and
then send him to the
right channel so if it's
STEMI, we're going to
call STEMI code and
call cardiology, you
know, to come and take
him to the cath lab.
Schist X-ray,
usually indicated if
we are suspicious
about, you know,
you want to rule out
underlying the reason
for chest pain when
it comes to the lung,
for example,
pneumothorax or pneumonia
um also i don't exclude
the fact sometimes
we have to do x-ray
for in the setting of
um mi and if your
patient is presenting
with um heart failure
kind of picture you
want to see if there
is fluid around the
lung or if um you know
um there is suspicion
about any other um
underlying condition.
But I don't think it's
the most appropriate
next step in our
patient at this time.
Troponin levels,
I think B is more
comprehensive and
more complete.
So trace B is
a way to go,
electrocardiogram and
the cardiac biomarkers,
which will include
the troponin.
and b is the correct
answer here let's
talk about ecg finding
and interpretation
and this slide
illustrates the stiny
ecg progression so
this is a normal ecg
um within minutes
you may see a
sign of myocardial
injury which
is called the
hyper acute T wave.
Within minutes to hours,
you may notice
ST elevation.
Within 1 hour to 12
hours,
you may notice ST elevation
and the appearance
of the T wave. You
see here, you it
was tiny here is more
deep and broader and
then within these from
stimmy you will see
still you can see st
elevation st elevation
and t wave inversion
which now started
to show you sign of
ischemia okay and then
after that within
weeks to months the T
wave recover and become
upright again and
then we are left
with something called
pathologic T wave at
least two millimeter 2
mm deep and 2 mm wide,
2 small square depth
and 2 small square
widths. We call it
pathologic U. It's
indicative of prior MI.
And here is a summary
slide also that
enforces what we said
before. so please keep in
mind and localization
of stimmy and non
-stimmy is important
because you want to know
the culprit artery
you want to know what
part of the heart
muscle is affected or
myocardial wall is
affected and and it's also
important when it
comes to the management
And the complications.
Actually, it ties
to everything.
So inferior wall MI,
represented by leads 2,
3, and AVF. And this
part of the heart is
supplied by the right
coronary artery. Sceptile
MI corresponds to
leads V1 and V2 and
is supplied by the left
anterior descending.
Anterior wall MI which
usually corresponds
to leads V3 to V4
and is supplied
by the left
anterior descending.
Anterolateral MI, which
corresponded to leads
V5 and V6, and
supplied by the left
anterior descending
and left circumflex.
The anterolateral,
left anterior
descending and left
circumflex. Lateral
wall is provided
by left circumflex
and corresponds to
leads 1 and AVL.
And here is another slide
that reinforced
that concept.
And our patient was
admitted to the hospital.
labs and serial ECGs
were performed and
here is his most recent
ECG and what do you
notice on that ECG and
when we look in the
context of MI to localize
we have to based on
our knowledge now we
know the localization of
the MI on ECG we have
to look at contiguous
leads leads that have
the same anatomic
importance leads that is
supplied by a specific
coronary artery and
as i started to review
that ecg i noticed
elevation st elevation in
lead one which also
will lead me to this is
a lateral lead which
will lead me to look at
lead avl and we can see
also here st elevation
do we see another st
elevation in other
leads i don't think
so even this a little
bit hyper but not it
has to be more at least
half of the preceding
r wave um you know but
there is st elevation
as per ecg here st
elevation in one and
AVL. You may find ST
depression in the inferior
leads, especially 3
and the AVF. We call it
reciprocally changes.
You don't need to
know a lot about
reciprocally changes
at this time, but know
the salient features
of this ECG when
it comes to ST
elevation in 1 and AVL.
And 1 and VL
correspond to what?
Lateral wall,
yeah, and usually
supplied by the
left circumflex. So
that will indicate
left circumflex
artery occlusion.
And here Here we go. So
the correct answer is A.
Let's talk about the
cardiac biomarkers
and labs.
So the cardiac
specific troponin T
and the cardiac
specific troponin I,
they are sensitive.
That means they
have a few false
negatives. And
they are specific,
they have few
false positives,
okay? And they
are the preferred
biochemical
markers for MR.
That's what we use in
current clinical practice
in the ED. If somebody
come with acute
chest pain, we do the
high sensitive troponins,
the high sensitive
troponins. High sensitive
troponins should be
drawn within 60 minutes
from patient arrival.
And usually we use
at least two sets, four
to six hours apart.
We rule our people
with two sets
separated by four
to six hours.
When it comes to highly
sensitive troponin,
it rises within
about four hours. It
peaks within 24 hours,
and it takes time
to return to baseline
about 7 to 10 days.
In contrast to the
CKMB, the creatine
kinase is specific to
the heart muscle, which
rises in 4 to 8
hours, so rises later.
and peaks in 16 to
24 hours and then
return to baseline
within 48 to 72 hours.
So the utility of
CKMP comes in action
when it comes to re
-infarction. A patient
was admitted to the
hospital with a STEMI
and presented with
chest pain. You
treated them and then
they are stabilized
five to six down the
road started to have
another chest pain so
that's the time when it
comes a utility of
cknp because if you can
if you check the
troponin they are still
elevated because they take
up to seven to ten days
to go back to normal
but when it comes to
cknp it takes maximum
three days to go back
to normal. So by three
days, we expect CKMP
to be normal.
Beyond the three
days, if your
patient had chest
pain and you find the
CKMP elevated,
that means patient
had another MI,
so re-infarction.
Other labs, for
sure, we have to have
routine baseline labs
for patient to evaluate
for metabolic
abnormalities like diabetes
or kidney disease,
also for anemia
or low platelets,
thrombocytopenia, and
coagulopathy, any
coagulation disorder. So
any patient presenting
with schist pain
have to have a routine
blood count, CDC,
chemistry panel,
which include blood
glucose, electrolytes,
kidney function, and
liver function, and
coagulation panel,
PT, PTT, and INR,
brothrombin time, partial
thromboblastin
time, and INR.
Schist radiograph
usually indicated when
you have to evaluate for
other causes of Schist
pain or discomfort,
but it has utility
sometimes in the setting
of MI if your patient
presenting with signs
of heart failure.
Sometimes you don't know
if the heart failure
started the heart
attack or the MI or
the MI puts the patient
in heart failure. So
sometimes you want
to have an x-ray done
to see if there are
fluids around the lung.
So sometimes it's
indicated still.
Echocardiogram
also is part,
you know, sometimes
they initially they
do a bedside echo,
Quick look by the
emergency physician,
but at certain
point when the
patient is stabilized,
they want to evaluate
their systolic
function and their
systolic function.
So it's usually done
during the admission
for somebody
presenting with MI.
Other tests are not
routinely done unless
a specific diagnosis
is suspected, like
computed tomographic
and geography. if i am
worried about aortic
dissection or pericardial
tamponade stuff like
that so um so they
are done on case by
case basis and this is a
summary slide um again
reinforcing what we
set and we're going
to switch gears to
the treatment and the
goal of therapy the
goal of therapy is
to reduce the risk
of death for sure
we don't want people
to die and extent of
the permanent cardiac
damage or cardiac
injury associated
with mi time is an
essence when it comes
to stimmy time is an
to stimmy um the
faster you diagnose
and and manage the
better the prognosis
um times and essence
is an essence when
it comes to the
myocardium and the second
point or bullet point
stay the same so
i'm not gonna read
it over and to manage
someone we have to
risk stratify them and
we use something
called the heart score
and heart is a mnemonic
for history ecg
age risk factors and
initial troconin and
we give them a
score based on these
parameters. And if your
patient has greater
than three, a score
of greater than three,
that's a greater risk
for acute coronary
syndrome and
warrant further work
up. So keep that in
mind, hard score.
Initial management,
there is something
called routine medical
therapy routine medical
therapy everybody
presenting with cyst
pain should have this
until they have this
regimen mona dash
unless they have certain
contraindication to
one of this medication
m stands for morphine
we give it for pain
relief O stands for
oxygen, we give it
also to a patient,
usually short of breath,
desetting, we need to
bring the oxygenation
up, so we use oxygen
judiciously, because
too much oxygen also
can harm the ischemic
myocardium, because of
the free radicals and
stuff. So we have to be
mindful using oxygen.
Nitrates, which are
arterial and which
are vasodilators,
vasodilators, and it
improves the coronary
blood flow and also
it relieves the
pain, so antiangina.
Aspirin. Aspirin
is the coronary
stone of therapy
when it comes to MI.
You give the
patient initially
to baby aspirin
to chew, and then
you put them
on maintenance.
Beta blockers. Beta
blockers are important.
If there is no
contraindication like
hypotension or anything,
you should start
them on beta blockers
because beta blockers
slow down the
heart. So when you
slow down the heart,
you relax the heart.
that it gives the
heart time more
time to uh get
blood filling
and get oxygenation
which is good
okay um then
ace or arp ace
inhibitors or
arp angiotensin
converting enzyme
inhibitors or
angiotensin
receptor blockers
if there is no
contraindication, if there
is no hypotension
especially in patients
with low systolic function
low ejection fraction,
very crucial to put
them on A's or R.
Statins, very important
to put them on
statins because they
are anti-inflammatory
effects, stabilize the
plaque the aceromatous
plaque and usually we
indicated high intensity
statin rosovastatin
40 or atorvastatin
80 milligram daily and
finally you put them
on anticoagulation
in preparation for
revascularization We use
usually heparin drip.
And here are more
information regarding
what I said. You can
read it on your own.
And now we give them
the initial management
that everybody get,
the monotash, and now
So we want to decide
what to do with them
in terms of initiating
perfusion therapy.
And reperfusion
therapy can be done via
PCI, percutaneous
coronary intervention,
or via fibrinolysis.
But keep in mind
fibrinolysis used
only in cases of
STEMI. If you don't
have access to PCI, and
it's not recommended
in cases of non
-STEMI because the
results are not good.
So fibrinolysis is
a way of reperfusion
when you don't have
a quick access to PCI
and only indicated
in STEMI and not
recommended in patients
with non-STEMI, okay?
Reperfusion also,
you know, we
call it, in case
of STEMI, we call
it emergent
revascularization.
When it comes to unstable
angina or non-STEMI,
Most of the time
we call it urgent
reperfusion That means
perfusion will be done
But not immediately
or emergent As in case
of STEMI Because as
you remember STEMI
is associated with 100
% occlusion The only
way to manage STEMI
Is to take them to
the cath lab and open
that artery with a
balloon and dilation
and stent placement.
In contrast to unstable
angina and non-stemy,
the obstruction is
about, reclusion
is about 90%,
which, okay, you
know, it's urgent
but not emergent.
But there are
some exceptions.
When it comes to
unstable angina and non
-STEMI, still
immediate or emergent
revascularization or
reperfusion indicated in the
following cases.
If your patient is
presenting with a cardiogenic
shock-like picture,
if your patient is
presenting with severe
heart failure, if
your patient continues
to have recurrent or
persistent anginal
pain despite intensive
medical treatment,
or if there is new
or worsening mitral
regurgitation or new
ventricular septal defect
which are called
mechanical complication
which we will talk
about it soon or if
there is sustained
ventricular arrhythmia
which is dangerous
and can lead to death.
So these are special
circumstances of
unstable angina and
non-stimi that warrant
immediate prompt
reperfusion, as in STEMI.
You know, STEMI,
immediate emergent
reperfusion.
Unstable angina,
non-STEMI,
urgent reperfusion
or revascularization,
except under the
previous circumstances
I mentioned,
which include
cardiogenic shock,
severe heart failure,
recurrent chest pain
despite intensive
medical treatment
presence of any mechanical
complication like
mitral regurgitation or
UVSD or sustained
ventricular arisnea and
under these
circumstances you have to
take patient with unstable
angina or non-stemy
immediately to the
cath lab So, and
let's talk about PCI.
PCI involves balloon
dilation and stent
placement via axis, usually
femoral axis or
radial axis. Now we
use femoral axis or
radial axis, okay? So
all patients with STEMI
who present within
12 hours of symptom
onset should undergo
immediate reperfusion,
immediate reperfusion.
The approach to
reperfusion depends on
the availability of
the PCI, as we said,
you know. so if you
have if your hospital
is PCI capable that
means they have
a cath lab the door
to balloon time goal
for PCI should be
90 minutes or less
from the time they
go through the door
of the hospital to
the time the balloon
is inflated and the
stint is placed in
the artery in the
CAS lab should be 90
minutes or less.
Please remember that.
In patients who
present within
12 hours of
symptom onset,
whom the first medical
contact to the PCI
interval is more than
120 minutes, So, and
they can safely
receive fibrinolytic
therapy, we use the
fibrinolysis, another
modality of, or alternative
to PCI, temporary
solution until we get
them to a PCI capable
hospital. So if your
patient presented
with symptoms suggestive
of STEMI, and,
okay, now you know it's
STEMI, okay, and they
are in a hospital
that PCI incapable,
that means they don't
have a cardiac cath
there. If you can
transfer them within 120
minutes to the neighboring
hospital, to the
next near hospital
to you, that's fine.
If it's the hospital,
the next hospital
or neighboring
hospital is more
than 120 minutes, you
may go with something
called the
fibrinolytic therapy.
and the recommendation
fibrinolytic therapy
should be received
within 30 minutes
from the first medical
contact. So you go
to the hospital,
this hospital doesn't
have a cath lab to
do PCI, balloon
dilation and stent
placement and the
neighboring hospital is
more than two hours
away within the first
Next, medical
contact, you have
to administer within 30
minutes the
fibrinolytic therapy.
Another way, until
you transfer them
to a PCI-capable
hospital. You're
still going to transfer
them, but after
you administer
fibrinolytic therapy.
because that maybe
resolves a clot you
know it's an emergency
situation you want
to deal with the
resources with it yeah
here are the contraindication
to fibrinolytic
therapy there
are some absolute
contraindications
some relevant relevant
contraindication but
you can read it on your
own And as we said,
fibrinolysis is not
recommended in non
-STEMI, only for STEMI.
What happened
to our patient?
Our patient, as
we saw on the
ECG, was found to
have lateral MI.
And our hospital
had cath lab.
That means it's
PCI capable.
So we took him, we
rushed him, we called
the cardiologist, we
rushed we called the
stiny code on him and
we took him to the
cath lab you see here
the left circumflex
is abruptly stopped
we don't see the
continuation of the
artery because the blood
supply has been cut
by the clots that
totally occluded the
vessel and we were
able to do a successful
PCI on him and
restore the flow of
the left circumflex
and the patient was
stabilized and was
discharged after a
week of hospital stay
And I'm going to meet
with you in a few
minutes for the
communication section.